Javier Guajardo

Software Engineer

Mexico

I'm a software engineer with 4+ years of software development experience, primarily as a full-stack developer.

I have worked with a diverse pool of technologies such as Ruby and Ruby on Rails, Python and Django, NodeJS, React, React Native. The types of applications that I have worked on are also varying. Examples are: Alexa skills, chatbots, mobile apps, backend APIs, frontend redesigns.

Contact

J +52 636 109 3561

f.javi.guajardo@gmail.com

in linkedin.com/in/fjaviguajardo

Skills

Programming Languages

- Python
- Javascript
- Ruby

Frameworks & Technologies

- Rails
- React JS
- React Native
- Django

Cloud Technologies

- AWS
- Google Cloud Platform

Languages:

- Spanish
- English

Experience

Software Engineer, Wizeline August 2018 - Present

Working as a full-stack developer. Responsible for collaborating with teams to create software solutions for big-name clients. Other than my day-to-day tasks, I've evaluated candidates by doing technical interviews for the refactoring session.

Newspaper Platform Migration

Technology stack: React, Node JS, AWS

This client is a large newspaper company, which has created an internal CMS platform for publishing new content. I was tasked with building features on top of this platform.

- Used React and Node JS to build React components based on designs for a newspaper layout, such as newspaper articles, newspaper headers, etc.
- Bootstrapped one of the key components in the project, which was fetching related content from an API, based on the article's content.
- Worked with an AWS architecture for handling multiple RSS feeds, which also was one of the key features.
- Shared clean code practices to team members by actively code reviewing pull requests, improving the project's code quality.
- Gave guidance and mentorship to help unblock newer team members that were joining the project.
- Was trusted by the team's delivery manager to be left as the last developer to close out the project, and had to work closely with leadership to finish up the last requirements.

Ordering App

Technology stack: Django, Python, Postgres, HTML, CSS, Javascript, Polymer

This is a startup that was acquired by a large software company. Since it was a small team, they hired us to build an Android app, build a backend API, and help with migrating to a redesigned frontend. I was the only engineer that worked on the backend API and the frontend redesign, and the only one that worked directly with a team of engineers from the original startup.

- Designed and built the mentioned backend API with Django and Django REST Framework. This API had 20+ endpoints, and I made sure that the code was unit tested up to 99%.
- Since I was the only one working directly with the client, I became the communication bridge between our team and the client. I had to come up with solutions for the backend API based on what the Android team was building, communicated those design decisions, figured out what was needed by the client, and helped troubleshoot issues regarding the backend that I was building.

Tracking Service

Technology stack: React Native, Google Cloud Platform

This was an Android app prototype built using React Native for a POC needed by a large software company. It had a deadline for one month, so it was really dynamic and needed constant communication between teammates and the client.

- Actively participated in high-level decisions with the team about prioritizing tasks and sprint planning, and made decisions on the technologies that were required for the project.
- Took ownership of the app's authentication by building it out using Google Auth and Firebase. - Built one of the key features of the app, which was creating and scheduling new appointments.
- Drove the initial and final product demos presented to the client.
- Was asked by the team's delivery manager to stay for an additional month to build the last features, fix bugs, and provide support.

Bots Platform

Technology stack: Node JS, Python, Alexa SDK

Worked on an Alexa Skill built for a large cinema company that launched with Alexa for Mexico. That deadline was for a one month, fixed deadline. We had to work with a technology that was new for the company at the time, so we had to come up with novel, creative ideas to be successful.

- Had to work extremely hard for the project to be delivered on time, staying at the office past midnight, on weekends, and on holidays. - Worked closely with the project's tech lead, assisting him with ideas for a custom SDK that we were building
- to create the skill.
- Wrote the conversation script for the skill, which took advantage of the custom SDK. - Worked closely with our UX designer to try to follow good design practices on voice interfaces. Researched
- and took an official Amazon workshop on the subject. - After the project's first approval, stayed as the lone developer for an additional six months to build
- enhancements, fix bugs, and gather new requirements.

Software Engineer Trainee, Wizeline June 2018 - August 2018

This was a three-month program, but the company decided to hire me for a full-time role in a month.

Ride-Sharing Service

Technology stack: Scala, Lift Framework, Maria DB, React JS

- While in this role, I showed my skills by working on a backend API for an internal ride-sharing service.

Web Developer, UACH IT Department May 2015 - June 2018 Worked as a full-stack developer, responsible for developing applications for this university in a team setting. I

worked here from my fourth semester in college until graduation.

Student Exchange

Technology stack: Rails, Postgres, HTML, CSS, Javascript This is a web application that serves as a platform for all of the university's students (50,000+) that wish to apply to an exchange program. This project completely removed the manual process being used beforehand. I was involved in the project from start to finish and took some of the most important design decisions for this

- Built the authentication and authorization pieces of the application. The authorization was a dynamic role-based system.
- Modeled and normalized the majority of the database tables. - Designed and remade the homepage from scratch (we were using a template beforehand).
- Migrated from Rails 4 to Rails 5 to take advantage of the real-time features that it offers for a messaging
- For the last few months became the sole project owner. Had to gather requirements from the stakeholder, design features and implement them.

Education

Software Engineering, UACH August 2013 - May 2017

Graduated with a 9.2 average on a 0-10 grading scale.